Everyone has a doubt whether
medical insurance or health insurance and
critical insurance are the same or different policies.
Everyone has a doubt whether they should take two policies. Okay, generally
everyone takes medical insurance or health
insurance, but
they do not know about critical illness policies. Today's video we are
going to watch is about critical illness
policies,
what is the differentiation of medical insurance and
what is the difference between these two policies.
We will see one of them, the best
critical illness policy, in
this video we are also
telling the details of this. Okay, so what is the difference between critical
illness and
health insurance policies? First,
when we get a health insurance policy, how much
sum insured do we take? Now, whether we
take three lakhs or five lakhs, how much sum insured do we take? That is a part of that sum
insured.
But in critical cases, we get a  In health insurance, you
only get its medical cost,
that is, out of these three lakhs, one lakh is
your hospital bill. Your
health insurance will be triggered only if you are admitted for 24 hours. When
that trigger occurs,
your doctor's fee
or the hospital's nursing fee
or room rent
are the expenses, and
they give reimbursement in cash. But in
critical illness, they give you a lump sum amount of
one lakh five hundred thousand or 10 lakh
five hundred thousand. If you get that illness,
they give you the full amount. So it's a lump sum
payment. Here, this is the actual
medical expenses they give. Okay,
then if you
are looking at the health insurance advantage, for
all the illnesses in health insurance, if
they are hospitalized and
admitted for 24 hours, they will pay the treatment cost for
it according to their terms and conditions.
In this case, only the
critical illness listed in the critical illness policy is
available. Now, in the current
plan, insurance policies that cover almost 92 critical
illnesses are
available in the market. Let's see about that
critical illness policy. Okay, the
name of this product is Critical Shield
Plus. It is
a general insurance
company that was introduced by ICCL. It is a private company. It is the biggest
general insurance
company.
Let's see what are the advantages of Critical Shield.
Critical Shield is the coverage of a
critical illness policy.
What are the key coverages and features of Critical Shield? First, they
cover 92 major and minor critical illnesses.
If we assume that its major is critical illness, then 100% off.  The
sum insured is how much sum insured we
take, they will give 100% sum insured for it,
and if 25% is minor, then
they give 25% of the sum insured of 25% critical illness.
They have classified critical illness into five buckets or five blocks.
That is the highlighting feature of this product, i.e.
Cancer and Blood Disorders, Heart
Related in Blood Vessels and Major Organs,
Nervous System and Other Illness.
They have divided it into five blocks. In each of these
five blocks,
they cover each critical illness. In these
major and minor buckets,
we
can see what is in these five blocks. In a block,
we take the sum insured and add it
to the sum insured of each block,
that is, you get a 10
If you take the sum insured of the lacs,
you will get a sum insured of 10 lacs in each block. In this, there
are 106 surgical procedures as optional benefits. Personal accident can be covered.
Cancer restoration is also a plan. Very
very important survival period i.e.
no survival period or 90 days waiting
period is not in this policy. In other words, when we say survival
period, normally all
critical illness policies that we
see after the illness has occurred, they have to survive for
30 days after the diagnosis of the illness,
then they will give the
sum insured of the critical illness.
Only after the 31st day, you can get a
claim in any other policy. In this
critical shield, there is no such survival
period clause. Once you have that illness and have been
diagnosed,
They will automatically give it to you even if you have not incurred any
medical expenses,
you are eligible for that amount as a lump sum.
Okay, then what are the
eligibility criteria? Adults
above 18 years and children up to three months old can be
covered, but
children can be covered only when adults are covered.
One year policy, two year policy,
maximum three year policy.
You can take this policy as a policy period.
What does the list of
critical illnesses cover? As
I said, they cover cancer and blood
disorders,
major and minor are listed here.
If you are diagnosed with it, you will get full
lump sum, if it is major, you will get 100% and
if it is minor, you will get 25%.
This is related to heart and blood vessel
diseases, major and minor.
What are the related illnesses that should be
covered in this? Then
what are the major and minor illnesses of the major organ? What are the listed illnesses that should be
covered?
Similarly, in each block,
this sum insured is fixed, then the nervous
system is related, what are the major and minor illnesses,
what are the critical illnesses that should be
covered in this? They have given that
all this is listed.
If we get any of these illnesses,
we will get the full sum insured. We will
get 25% of the major and minor that we get 100%. Then the list of
critical illnesses and other illnesses is
shown in this. So, mostly
almost 92 major and minor illnesses are
covered in this. So,
what is the
premium chart for this? If the premium chart is 20,
as I saw, we cannot take it as a family, we have to
take it as an individual policy.  Every
individual should take an individual policy. The
premium chart for individual policies up to 55 years is
given here from 5 lakhs to 40
lakhs. You
can take it even if you want, but the maximum sum insured available
is 40 lakhs. Within that 40 lakhs, it is now
above 20 lakhs.
Medical checkups will be done
according to their age and illness. So, if they are
normally medically fit, we
can take this policy only if we do not have any critical illness at present. So, thanks for watching. If you
have any doubts or clarifications, if you are interested in taking this product,
you can contact this number.
I am a financial advisor. I have 22 years
of insurance experience.
I have worked in various insurance companies. So,
all the terms and conditions related to claims as well as policy are explained.  I
present you a good product after studying,
thanks a lot.